Welcome  to   the  Vernon  Smith   Experimental  Economics
Laboratory.  Please  carefully  watch  these  video
instructions  and  follow  along  on  the  paper  copy
at  your  desk.   Experiment  Overview  You  are  about
to  participate  in  an   experiment  in  the  economics
of  decision-making.  If  you  listen  carefully,
you  could  earn  a  large  amount  of  money,  that
will  be  paid  to  you  in  cash,  in  private,  at
the  end  of  the  experiment.  It  is  important
that  you  remain  silent  and  do  not  look  at
other  people's  work.  If  you  have  any  questions,
or  need  any  assistance  of  any  kind,   please
raise  your  hand  and  an  experimenter  will  help
you  out.   During  the  experiment,   do  not  talk,
laugh  or  exclaim  out  loud  and  be  sure  to   keep
your  eyes  on  your  screen  only.  In  addition,
please  turn  off  your  cell  phones,  etc.  and
put  them  away  during  the  experiment.  Anybody
that  violates  these  rules  will  be  asked  to
leave  and  will  not  be  paid.   We  expect,  and
appreciate  your  cooperation.   Agenda   1.  We  will
first  go  over  the  instructions.   2.  Then  we
will  have  a  practice  match  to  learn  the  interface.
3.  Next,  there  will  be  a  quiz  with  10  questions
to  make  sure  everyone  understands  the  instructions.
All  10  questions  will  refer  to  these  instructions
so  you  should  follow  them  carefully.   If  you
answer  all  questions  correctly  you  will  earn
10  dollars.   If  you  answer  at  least  one  question
incorrectly  you  will  earn  nothing,  at  which
point  you  will  not  need  to  answer  any  more
questions.   You  will  have  10  minutes  to  answer
the  10  questions.   4.  After  the  quiz,  you  will
have  10  minutes  to  prepare  for  the  experiment.
In  the  experiment  you  will  be  working  with
a  fictitious  currency  called  Francs.  You  will
be  paid  in  US  Dollars  at  the  end  of  the  experiment.
The  exchange  rate  today  is:  1250  Francs  equals
1  USD.   Experiment  Details   This  experiment  consists
of  ten  matches.   Prior  to  start  of  the  experiment,
all  participants  may  be  split  into  two  groups.
The  groups  will  stay  fixed  and  you  will  know
the  number  of  participants  in  your  group  throughout
the  experiment.   At  the  beginning  of  each  match,
you  will  be  paired  randomly  with  one  other
participant  from  your  group.  You  will  remain
matched  with  this  same  participant  until  the
end  of  the  match,  but  then  will  be  paired
with  another  randomly  selected  participant  from
your  group  in  the  following  match.  Each  match
will  have  the  same  structure,   but  may  contain
different  numbers  of  periods.   You  will  remain
anonymous  throughout  the  experiment.  You  will
not  know  the  identity  of  the  participant  that
you  are  paired  with,  and  they  will  not  know
your  identity.   The  choices  made  by  you,  and
the  participant  you  are  paired  with,  have  no
effect  on  the  payoffs  of  participants  in  other
pairs,  and  vice  versa.  Therefore,  your  payoff
in  a  given  match  is  based  solely  on  the  choices
made  by  you  and  the  participant  that  you  are
paired  with.   Next,  Let's  Look  at  the  experimental
Interface  Specific  Instructions  for  Each  Period
Your  payoff  in  each  period  will  depend  on  your
choice  and  the  choice  of  the  participant  that
you  are  paired  with.  You  will  choose  one  of
two  options,  either  W  or  Y.  You  will  be  able
to  see  the  payoffs  for  each  combination  of
choices  for  you  and  the  participant  that  you
are  paired  with.  These  payoffs  will  remain  the
same  throughout  the  entire  experiment  (all  matches).
The  payoffs  will  be  displayed  in  a  table  like
this:  In  this  example  above,  the  rows  are  the
following:   Row  #1  - Your  choice  (either  W  or
Y  in  this  example)   Row  #2  - Other's  choice
(either  W  or  Y  in  this  example)   Row  #3  - Your
payoff.   Row  #4  - Other's  payoff.   Row  #5  - Total
number  of  times  that  that  combination  has  been
played  this  match.  Examples:  In  the  table  above,
if  you  choose  W  and   the  participant  that
you  are  paired  with  chooses  Y,  then   you  receive
a  payoff  of  3,  and   the  participant  that  you
are  paired  with  receives  a  payoff  of  4.   This
combination  has  occurred  19  times  so  far  this
match.   If  you  choose  W  and   the  participant
that  you  are  paired  with  chooses  W,  then   you
receive  a  payoff  of  7,  and   the  participant
that  you  are  paired  with  receives  a  payoff
of  8.   This  combination  has  occurred  6  times
so  far  this  match.   If  you  choose  Y  and   the
participant  you  are  paired  with  chooses  Y,  then
you  receive  a  payoff  of  1,  and   the  participant
that  you  are  paired  with  receives  a  payoff
of  2.   This  combination  has  occurred  6  times
so  far  this  match.   History  As  the  match  progresses,
you  will  see  the  history  of  play  across  the
top  of  the  screen,  displayed  like  this:   This
history  displays   the  period  (labeled  Period),
your  choice  in  that  period  (labeled  My  Choice),
the  choice  of  the  participant  you  are  paired
with  in  that  period  (labeled  Other's  Choice),
and   the  payoff  for  that  period  (labeled  My
Payoff).  For  example,  in  the  above  history,
in  period  39,   you  played  W,   the  participant
you  are  paired  with  played  Y,   and  you  received
a  payoff  of  3.   Rules  Rather  than  directly
making  choices  of  W  or  Y,  you  will  develop
a  set  of  rules  which  will  automatically  make
choices  for  you.   The  set  of  rules  will  appear
in  the  middle  of  the  screen.   You  will  be
able  to  construct  rules  using  the  rule  constructor
at  the  bottom  of  the  screen.   A  rule  consists
of  two  parts:   Input  Sequence  - A  sequence  of
choices  made  by  you  and  the  participant  you
are  paired  with.   Output  - A  choice  to  be  made
by  you  after  the  input  sequence  occurs.   Some
example  rules  are  displayed  below:   For  example,
Rule  #2  has  an  input  sequence  of   (Y,Y),   (W,W),
(Y,W)  and  an  output  of   W.  This  means  that
if  you  have  played   Y,  W,  and  then  Y  in  the
last  three  periods,  and  the  participant  that
you  are  paired  with  has  played   Y,  W,  and
then  W,  this  rule  will  lead  you  to  play   W
in  the  next  period.  As  play  progresses  you
will  develop  a  set  of  rules  that  will  be  used
to  make  your  choices.  Play  will  proceed  as
follows:  Each  period,   your  set  of  rules  will
select  the  choice  to  be  made  next  period.  The
rule  that  will  be  used  to  make  the  choice
will  be  highlighted.  The  corresponding   sequence
in  the  history  will  be  highlighted.  A   preview
of  the  choice  to  be  made  next  period  will
be  shown  as  a  lightly  colored  cell  on  the
history  of  play.  In  order  to  move  to  the  next
period,  you  have  to  confirm  the  choice  by  clicking
on  the  corresponding  history  cell.   Once  you
have  confirmed  your  choice,  the  light  color
will  turn  to  a  regular  color,  and  you  may
need  to  wait  for  the  participant  that  you  are
paired  with  to  make  their  choice.   There  are
several  ways  that  you  can  modify  your  rules
during  the  experiment.  1.   First,  you  can  use
the  rule  constructor  in  the  bottom  center  of
the  screen.   Press  the  plus  button  to  add  more
columns,   or  one  of  the  minus  buttons  to  subtract
columns.  Click  on  the  question  marks  to  fill
in  the  boxes.  When  you  click  on  a  question
mark,   either  a  W  or  a  Y  will  appear.  If
you  click  on  a  W,   it  will  switch  to  a  Y,
and  if  you  click  on  a  Y,   it  will  switch
to  a  W.   Once  you  have  completely  filled  in
the  rule  (leaving  no  question  marks),   the  add
rule  button  will  appear,   and  the  rule  can
be  added  to  your  set.  2.  Second,  if  you  look
at  a  rule  in  the  set,   you  will  notice  a
green  copy  button,   and  a  red  delete  button.
If  you   press  the  green  copy  button,  it  will
copy  the  rule  down  to  the  constructor,   and
you  will  be  able  to  create  a  similar  rule.
If  you   press  the  red  delete  button,  it  will
delete  the  rule  from  the   set.  3.  Since  your
rule  set  needs  to  make  a  single  choice  each
period,  it  is  not  possible  to  have  two  rules
with  the  same  input  sequence,  but  with  different
outputs.   If  you  create  a  rule  that  has  the
same  input  sequence  but  a  different  output,
you  will  get  an  error  that   says  'Conflicting
rule  in  set",  and  a   button  that  says  'Switch
Rule"  will  appear.  If  you  press  this  button,
it  will  delete  the   conflicting  rule  from  the
rule  set,   and  add  the  rule  from  the   constructor.
The  length  of  the  rule  is  measured  by  the
length  of  the  input  sequence.  So   rule  #2,
and   rule  #3  have  a  length  of  3,  and   rule
#4  has  a  length  of  2.  A  rule  of  length  n
is  said  to  fit  the  history  if  the  input  sequence
matches  the  last  n  periods  of  the  history.
For  example,  since  the  last  three  periods  of
play  in  the  above  history   (periods  42  through
44)  have  been   (Y,  Y),   (W,  W),  and   (Y,  W),
and  that  sequence  is  also  the  input  for   rule
#2,  then  rule  #2  is  said  to  fit  the  history.
Similarly,  given  the  above  history,  we  can  see
that   rule  #4  fits  the  history,  but   rule  #3
does  not  fit  the  history.  If  more  than  one
rule  fits  the  history,  then  the  rule  with  the
longer  length  will  determine  the  choice.  For
example,  given  the  above  history  since  both
rule  #2,  and   rule  #4  fit  the  history,   rule
#2  will  be  used  to  make  your  choice,  since
it  is  longer.  Therefore,  given  the  history,
and  the  rule  set,  your  choice  next  period  will
be  W,  as  prescribed  by   rule  #2.   If  no  rules
fit  the  history,  then  your   Default  Rule  will
be  selected.  The  default  rule  will  only  be
used  when  no  rules  fit  the  history.   To  select
your  default  rule  select  either   W,  or   Y,
in  the  bottom  left  of  your  screen.  Additionally,
you  have  to  select  the   First  Period  rule.
The  first  period  rule  will  only  be  used  in
the  first  period  of  the  match.  To  select  your
first  period  rule  select  either   W,  or   Y,
in  the  bottom  left  of  your  screen.   Additional
Examples  In  the  example  above,   Rule  #4,  and
Rule  #9,  both  fit  the  history.  However,  rule
#9  will  be  selected  because  it  is  longer.  Therefore,
W  will  be  played  in  the  next  period,   as
prescribed  by  rule  #9.  For  the  example  above,
how  can  we  change  the  rule  set  to  ensure  that
Y  is  played  next  period.  There  are  several
ways  to  make  changes  to  the  rule  set  in  order
for  Y  to  be  played.  First,  you  can  delete
Rule  #9,  which  would  cause   Rule  #4  to  be
the  longest  rule  that  fits  the  history,   and
therefore  would  lead  to  Y  being  played  next
period.   Second,  you   can  add  a  longer  rule
that  fits  the  history  that  has  Y  as  the  output.
Since  you  added  a  longer  rule  that  fits  the
history,  that  rule  will  be  used  to  make  the
choice,  and  will  select  Y  as  the  choice  for
next  period.   Number  of  Periods  Per  Match  The
number  of  periods  in  each  match  will  be  determined
randomly  using  the  following  procedure.  At  the
end  of  each  period,   a  number  will  be  chosen
randomly  from  the  set  of  numbers   {1,2,3,  up
to,48,49,50},  where  each  number  is  equally  likely.
If  the  number  is  1,  then  the  match  will  end.
If  the  number  is  not  1,  then  the  match  will
continue.  The  number  will  always  be  placed  back
into  the  set  after  it  is  drawn.  Thus,  in  any
period  there  is  a  2  percent  CHANCE  that  the
match  will  end,  and  a  98  percent  CHANCE  that
the  match  will  have  another  period.  Therefore,
the  expected  number  of  periods  in  each  match
will  be  50.   This  procedure  has  been  performed
on  the  computer  before  the  experiment.  Therefore,
you  will  not  see  the  number  selected  from  {1,2,3,
up  to,48,49,50}.  To  ensure  that  the  length  of
the  match  is  not  dependent  on  your  play,  the
number  of  periods  for  each  match  has  be  written
on  the  board  before  the  experiment,  and  will
be  uncovered  at  the  end  of  the  experiment.
Your  choices  will  be  determined   automatically
from  your  rule  set.  However,  you  will  need
to  confirm  the   choice  within  an  allotted  amount
of  time.  To  confirm  your  choice,   click  on
your  action  for  the  next  period  within  the
history  at  the  top  of  the  screen.  If  you  don't
confirm  the  choice  within  the  allotted  amount
of  time,   then  the  choice  will  be  confirmed
automatically  at  the  end  of  the  allotted  time.
The  experiment  will  not  be  able  to  proceed
until  everyone  confirms  their  choices.   Everyone
in  your  group  will  have  the  same  amount  of
time  allotted  in  each  period.   Additional  Information
about  Matches  During  matches  1  through  10  you
will  be  able  to  construct  the  set  of  rules
to  make  your  choices.   All  of  the  rules  in
your  set  at  the  end  of  one  match  will  remain
in  your  set  at  the  start  of  the  next  match.
Before  the  first  match,   you  will  have  1  minute
to  look  over  the  payoffs,   and  an  additional
10  minute  to  construct  your  rules.   Editing
your  set  of  rules  In  the  experiment  today  you
will  need  to  pay  a  cost  to  edit  rules  during
the  match.  More  specifically,  Before  each  match
starts,  you  can  make  changes  to  your  set  of
rules  at  no  cost.  After  each  match  starts,
if  you  want  to  make  changes  to  your  set  of
rules,   you  must  click  the  'Unlock  Rules"  button.
The  cost  for  clicking  the  'Unlock  Rules"  button
is  0  Francs.  The  total  cost  incurred  in  all
matches   will  be  displayed  at  the  top  of  the
screen  in  red.  You  will  be  able  to  edit  your
rules  for  the  duration  of  one  period.  Once
you  are  done  editing  your  rules  you  may  click
the  'Lock  Rules"   button.  If  you  don't  want
to  make  changes  to  your  set  of  rules,  you
may  choose  not  to  click  the  'Unlock  Rule"  button.
Then  you  will  not  incur  the  cost  of  0  Francs.
In  either  case,  you  will  need  to  confirm  the
choice  made  within  the  time  limit  set  for  each
period.  If  the  time  limit  within  a  period  is
reached,  your  rules  will  become  locked,  your
choice  will  be  confirmed  automatically,  and  you
will  proceed  to  the  next  period.   Starting  Rules
Prior  to  the  start  of  the  experiment  you  will
have  10  minutes  to  construct  your  starting  set
of  rules.  During  that  time,  you  will  be  presented
with  a  split-screen  view  of  of  the  construction
screen.  In  this  view,  you  will  have  an  opportunity
to  test  what  your  rule  set  will  select  as
an  output  for  a  variety  of  hypothetical  histories.
The  split-screen  will  consist  of  two  sides.
The  right  side  is  the  Starting  Rules  side.
Rules  added  to  this  side  will  be  added  to
your  rule  set  at  the  start  of  the  first  match.
The  left  side  is  the  Hypothetical  Rules  side.
Rules  added  to  this  side  can  be  used  to  test
to  see  what  choices  different  combinations  of
rules  will  lead  to.  You  will  be  able  to  move
rules  from  the  Hypothetical  Rules  side  to  the
Starting  Rules  side   by  clicking  the  blue  move
button.  To  delete  rules  from  either  side,   you
need  to  click  the  delete  button.  You  will  be
able  to  see  what  choice   your  hypothetical,
and   your  starting  rule  sets  select  as  a  choice
for  next  period,  for  each  of  the  hypothetical
histories  that  you  construct.  Notice  that  you
will  be  able  to  construct,  and  store,  multiple
histories   at  the  same  time.  You  can  view  one
of  the  other  hypothetical  histories  by  clicking
the   History  #  button  at  the  top  of  the  Hypothetical
Rules  side.  You  can  add  a  new  hypothetical
history  by  clicking  the   New  button  at  the
top  of  the  Hypothetical  Rules  side.  To  construct
a  hypothetical  history  you  will  need  to  click
on  the   question  marks  in  that  history.  You
don't  need  to  fill  out  the  entire  history  to
see  what  choice  your  rule  set  will  make.  Therefore,
it  is  useful  to  start  filling  out  the  new
histories  from  the  most  recent  periods  on  the
right  side.  Let's  look  at  an  example.   Five
periods  of  hypothetical  History  #4  have  been
filled  in.   The  hypothetical  rule  set  will  play
W  after  this  history  occurs.   The  starting  rule
set  will  play  Y  after  this  history  occurs.
Let's  look  at  another  example.   14  periods
of  hypothetical  History  #3  have  been  filled
in.   The  hypothetical  rule  set  will  play  Y
after  this  history  occurs.   The  starting  rule
set  will  play  Y  after  this  history  occurs.
You  will  be  able  to  make  changes  to  your  Hypothetical
Rules,  and  your  Starting  Rules,  for  the  duration
of  the  10  minutes.  After  the  ten  minutes  are
up,  rules  that  are  on  the  Starting  Rules  side
will  be  your  starting  rules  for  the  experiment.
Payoffs   At  the  end  of  the  experiment,  you
will  be  paid  in  cash.   Your  payoff  at  the
end  of  the  experiment  will  be  the  sum  of  the
payoffs  for  each  period.   Reminder,  the  exchange
rate  today  is  1250  Francs  equals  1  dollar.
Practice  Match  Next,  there  will  be  a  practice
match  to  make  sure  that  you  are  comfortable
with  the  interface.  It  is  important  to  note
that  in  this  practice  match,   you  will  NOT
be  paid  for  the  choices  made.   the  payoffs
are  all  listed  as  0,  so  that  you  can  focus
on  getting  comfortable  with  the  interface,  rather
than  focusing  on  the  payoffs.   You  are  NOT
paired  with  another  participant.  Your  opponent
for  the  practice  match  is  a  computer  that  is